Finding Aid for Charles I. Walker Collection, 1817-1887
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles I. Walker Collection 1817-18871817-1825
Walker, Charles I. (Charles Irish), collector
1 traycase
Professor of law at the University of Michigan. Papers collected relating to the founding of the University; include original draft of the act to establish the Catholepistemiad, table explaining meaning of names of professorships, various drafts and amendments, receipts, correspondence, and related documents; contain papers drafted or signed by Augustus B. Woodward, John Monteith, and William Woodbridge.
874 AC
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the Library of the University of Michigan. Donor no. 1278
The collection is open for research. The collection is available for use only during regular weekday hours.
Professor of law at the University of Michigan.
Collected documents relating to the founding of the University, including original draft of the act to establish the Catholepistemiad, table explaining meaning of names of professorships, various drafts and amendments, receipts, correspondence, and related documents; contain papers drafted or signed by Augustus B. Woodward, John Monteith, and William Woodbridge.
Subjects:
Catholepistemiad (Detroit, Mich.); University of Michigan--History.
Contributors:
Monteith, John, 1788-1868.; Woodbridge, William, 1780-1861.; Woodward, Augustus B. (Augustus Brevoort), d. 1827.
- University of Michigan founding documents
  - Letter to James B. Angell from Charles I. Walker donating these early letters to the University of Michigan, February 11, 1885 (Box 1)
    (item no. A)
  - The original draft of the act to establish the Catholepistemiad, or University of Michigania, in the handwriting of its author, Judge Augustus B. Woodward; and drafts of other legislation, file dateNovember 7, 1817 (Box 1)
    (item no. 1)
  - A table explaining the meaning of the names of the professorships mentioned in the act (Box 1)
    (in the handwriting of Judge Augustus B. Woodward)
    (item no. 2)
  - Memoranda of proposed amendments to Woodward's draft (Box 1)
    (item no. 3)
  - A draft of an act prepared in, 1818 to provide for the election of Regents of the University (in the handwriting of Judge Woodward and signed by him) (Box 1)
    (item no. 4)
  - A rough draft of the act of 1821 amending the act to establish the Catholepistemiad, and providing for Regents (in the handwriting of Judge Woodward) (Box 1)
    (item no. 5)
  - A draft of a new act "to institute a University within the Territory of Michigan", 1825 (Box 1)
    (item no. 6)
  - A draft of a new act "to institute a University within the Territory of Michigan", undated (Box 1)
    (item no. 7)
  - An enactment by the University of Michigania that subscribers should not be required to pay more than fifty dollars a year; passed, September 12, 1817, (formally signed by John Monteith, President, and attested by J. L. Whiting, Register) (Box 1)
    (item no. 8)
  - Enactment signed and attested, October 3, 1817 (Box 1)
    (A fund had been raised for the sufferers of the fire of 1805 in Detroit, Montreal, and elsewhere. The money had not been paid to the sufferers, and this act was to indemnify the holders of the money if they paid it to the University)
    (item no. 9)
  - An appointment by John Monteith, President, of George McDougall as Trustee and Visitor of the Classical Academy of Detroit, February 26, 1818 (Box 1)
    (item no. 10)
  - A receipt to Judge A. B. Woodward for his subscription to the University for the year, 1817, (signed by Duncan Reid, Collector) (Box 1)
    (item no. 11)
  - Three letters from the Judge B. F. H. Witherell to Judge Woodward, calling upon him to pay his subscription to the University (Box 1)
    (The balance was $87.50)
    (item no. 12)
  - A brief history of the University of Michigan, by C. I. Walker, published in the newspapers, 1869 (Box 1)
    (item no. 13)
  - A letter from Governor William Woodbridge to Judge Woodward making reference to those who should be chosen President and the Professors at the opening of the Catholepistemiad, undated (Box 1)
    (item no. 14)
  - Other documents (letter and enclosures)
    (item no. 15)
    - Letter from Judge James V. Campbell (with enclosures), March 15, 1887 (Box 1)
    - Report of the Committee on the organization, and government of the University, March 17, 1838, (signed Henry R. Schoolcraft, chairman) (Box 1)
    - Report of the Monroe Branch, University of Michigan, March 9, 1838, (signed S. Center, principal) (Box 1)